Hello, and welcome to
San Houston State
University's
alternative
certification program.
We're excited you've
chosen SHSU and
are on your pathway to
becoming a
BearCat teacher.
In this video, we want to
introduce you to
the program and
the important steps
you will take to
becoming certified
as a Texas educator.
We will also introduce
you to Blackboard
and explain
the pre internship
phase of this program.
If you are not seeing
the PowerPoint
slides as the largest
part of the screen,
move your cursor to
the upper right
hand corner of
the screen and find
the two arrows.
Clicking on those
arrows will
make the PowerPoint
slides larger.
To begin, we want to
recognize and thank
the faculty who created
the alternative
certification program.
This program has
its roots in
the high quality teacher
preparation program that
has existed at Sam
Houston State University
since 18 79.
SHSU has a long
tradition of
preparing excellent
educators
for Texas schools.
This team of professors
dedicate themselves
to preparing
an alternative
certification program
that upholds the
proud tradition and
prepares teachers to be
successful in day one
in today's classroom.
We recognize and
appreciate their hard work
and ongoing dedication
to educator preparation.
We'll do a quick tour
through Blackboard.
Blackboard holds all of
the key components and
tasks of
the pre internship
portion of the program.
If you were ever unsure
about what needs to
be completed in order to
begin your internship,
you can find the
answers here.
Because you have
found this video,
you must have found
the Start Here section
and found welcome to
the teacher
certification program.
In this section, you will
also see other
helpful sections.
Work through
these sections
and watch the videos.
They provide helpful
information.
One of these tabs is
the ACP checklist.
This checklist
contains a roadmap
to beginning
your internship.
This program is
self paced and
these steps do not have
to be completed in order.
There are three
important milestones
in the pre internship
phase of this program,
and we'll briefly
talk about
each one and then go
into more detail.
First, CIED 50 301.
Within this course
are modules,
tasks, certifications,
and observation
and interaction
requirements
that need to be
completed in order to
receive your intern
certificate.
CIED 50 301 must be
completed in order to
qualify for internship.
Completion of this
course gives you
150 C hours of
training that
TEA requires for
intern certification.
The second essential
component for
internship is
passing your required
Texas certification exams.
Everyone must pass
a content area exam
related to your
certification area.
SHSU has a contract
with 240 tutoring,
which provides free
practice tests
and discounted
testing support.
Once you have passed
your content area
practice test,
a full length test
with 80% or higher,
you can request test
approval through
ACP at Hsu dot EDU.
If you are certifying
in EC three,
EC six or 48
core subjects,
48 ELAR or 48 social
studies with ELAR.
The state of Texas
requires that
you also pass
the science of
teaching reading
or the STR exam.
Our Student Academic
Success Center
in the Newton
Gresham Library on
campus and the Academic
Success Center at
the Woodlands campus
offer testing support,
test taking strategies,
writing coaching
for the STR,
and study strategies
coaching.
Within the modules
of 50 301,
there is information
about completing
your required
observation hours,
which is the
third essential
step to internship.
The state of Texas
requires 50 hours of
classroom observations
and student interactions
for all teacher
candidates.
This includes at
least 25 hours of in
person student
interactions
in a Texas classroom.
This can be
completed doing
short term substituting,
working as an
educational aid,
or volunteering
in a classroom
during the regular
school day.
But these student
interactions need to be
a meaningful part of
the interaction time that
you are with
these students.
The module in 50 301
will explain this
in more detail.
Up to 25 hours
can be completed
through watching
videos of high quality
classroom instruction
or observing in
a classroom.
Again, the details
of this requirement
is found in
Module in 50 301.
Once you have completed
the course CIED 50 301,
passed your content test,
and completed
your 50 hours
of observations
and interactions,
you will be eligible to
begin your internship.
An intern is hired as
the teacher of record by
a school district,
charter school,
or accredited
private school
and is paid as a teacher
with full benefits
and with teacher
retirement.
This is when you begin
your teaching career.
Because you are
hired by a school,
you will need to apply
for jobs and
find a position.
Be wise, recognize that
you have choices
and options.
Find the position that
is right for you.
The second course,
CIED 50 302,
can be completed before
your internship or
during your internship.
I would highly recommend
that you complete
as much as 50 302 as
possible before you
begin teaching.
You have one year to
complete both courses.
You have a lot to do
as a new teacher.
Anything you can
do before you
begin your internship
will help you to
be more successful
and make
that first year of
teaching easier for you.
You have two internship
courses that
you will register
for as an intern,
CIED 53 98 during
your first semester
of internship
and CIED 53 99
during your second
semester of internship.
Before you can be
recommended for
standard certification
with TEA,
there is one final
test you must take.
You will need to take
and pass the PPR exam,
pedagogy and professional
responsibilities.
You can prepare
for and pass
this test at any time
during your program.
You will also be creating
a portfolio during
your program known
as the T CAR CAR.
This will be explained
in the modules as well.
Once you have completed
all of the requirements
and successfully completed
your internship,
your principal,
mentor, and SHSU can
recommend you for standard
teaching certification
with the state of Texas.
Again, this program
is self paced.
You can complete these
steps out of order.
Work ahead before your
internship as
much as you can,
so you can focus
on teaching with
a broad base of
knowledge and skills.
I know this is a
lot of information.
Please feel free to email
your professor
or the program
with any questions
you have.
You have links to get
your answers to
the questions
within the modules
in Blackboard,
and we are always
here to help you.
Blackboard will guide you
through all of the
phases of the program.
The next section of
Blackboard covers
the details of
the certification
exam requirements.
This section will give you
the information you
need to prepare for and
pass the test that
Texas requires in
order for you to
receive your teaching
certification.
Work through this section
and watch the videos.
Here, you will learn about
the resources
available to you to
prepare for and
be approved to
take your
certification tests.
There are several
important resources
here to help you
prepare for testing.
Always remember the
Academic Success Center
at SHSU is available
to help you.
They can provide one on
one support and provide
coaching that can increase
your chances for success.
The next section provide
details about the
field experiences and
observation hours
required by the state of
Texas for all Texas
teachers candidates.
You are required
to complete
50 hours of observations,
at least 25 hours of
which must involve
interactions
with students in an
authentic school setting
in a TEA
accredited school.
These interactions can be
done working with
small groups,
providing support to
individual students
during a class session,
or supporting a teacher
in teaching a whole class.
You are not required
to plan with
a teacher or
teach the class,
but you should be
involved with
students during
the regular school day
in a meaningful way.
These observations
must be done during
the regular school hours
and include a focus on
the Texas essential
knowledge and skills or
Ts Field experiences can
be completed as an
educational aide,
a substitute teacher,
or as a teacher
of record if you
are working in the
classroom already as
a DOI waiver teacher.
Up to 25 hours of field
experience hours can
be completed
virtually through
watching videos of
classroom instruction.
The module and Blackboard
has links to classroom
videos that you can use
for these virtual
observations.
All observations
require completion
of a log and a
written reflection.
In this reflection,
talk about what you
would do differently,
how you could
apply some of
these strategies in
your own classroom,
what was helpful
and useful
to students, how
students react,
wired reflection
that gives some
insight into how
you were impacted or
learned from these videos.
If you're observing
in a classroom,
the teacher of record
in the classroom
will need to verify your
hours through email.
If you are working
in a school
as an instructional aide,
substitute teacher or
teacher of record,
your principal can
verify your hours
or HR can verify the
hours in the district.
Virtual hours can be
verified by your
instructor or by
emailing ACP at s dot ed.
This would be for
the video observations
that you complete.
Look through the modules,
watch the videos.
If you have any
additional questions,
please contact
your instructor
or email the program.
This section
contains a summary
of what you need
to do in order
to qualify for
a statement of
eligibility or an SOE,
and to apply for an
intern certificate
with the Texas
Education Agency.
The three steps are 150
hours of coursework,
which is completed by
finishing CIED 50 301,
passing the
required tests,
which includes your
content test and
possibly the STR depending
on your
certification area.
And completing 50 hours of
field observations and
student interactions.
Once these things
have been completed,
you can email the program
or work with
your professor.
We can issue your
statement of eligibility,
and you can begin
applying for
positions in
school districts.
Third important
step to internship
is completing that 150
hours of coursework.
For this program, you
will need a text.
You can subscribe to
an e text through Pearson.
This text is closely
linked to the modules,
and you will need to use
it to pass the course.
The link in 50 301
will guide you
to obtaining
a subscription through
Pearson for the e text.
If you would like a
hard copy of the text,
I would recommend
that you contact
Pearson directly.
The text is quite
expensive on Amazon.
It is important that you
get the tenth edition.
There's an
option on Amazon
to get the Kindle edition
if that works
better for you or
is most cost effective.
Research your options
and decide what form of
text you would be
most beneficial
for you to use.
There are five TEA
required trainings
embedded within
the modules.
You need to make
sure that you pass
each one of
those trainings
and pass the test.
Add these training
certificates
to your portfolio.
If you are certifying
in PK three,
your modules are
the ECHE modules
at the bottom
of Blackboard.
Make sure you
are completing
the correct modules and
working through the
correct modules.
If you are not
in PK three,
you do not complete
those ECHE modules.
If you have
questions on finding
the right modules and the
right information or
getting the text,
please contact
your instructor.
The very last section
in Blackboard
describes the T
car portfolio.
You will be creating
this portfolio all the
way along the pathway
to certification.
It is important that you
be aware of what you
should be
gathering in your
portfolio from day
one in the program.
Be sure to look at
the short video
on this page and
skim through
the resource guides
so you understand
the expectations for
this capstone portfolio.
Thank you for
taking your time
to walk through
this with me.
As always, we
are here to help
you in any way that
we possibly can.
You are well supported
in this program,
but you need to
reach out sometimes.
Make sure you ask
the questions
you need to ask,
get the support
you need to get.
The college has a lot of
rich resources that can
help you in any areas.
If you ever run into
difficulties or have
a need for extra help or
assistance or
have questions,
our email is
ACP at sts.org.
Please reach out. We're so
excited to have you
here and have you
in our program,
and we're excited to
have you help you to get
along your
pathway to become
a certified
teacher in Texas.